Guide to the New-York Historical Society Membership Records 1804-1983 NYHS-RG 9
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Annual Member Lists, 1873-1978; 6.92 Linear feet
  - Loose Documents, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Member List, 1969 (Volume RG9.73, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1970 (Volume RG9.74, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Member List, 1971 (Volume RG9.75, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Member List, 1972 (Volume RG9.76, Folder -)
    Access restriction: This volume shows signs of having been damaged by water. Most of its pages are stuck together. It can be used only with the assistance of conservation staff.
  - Member List, 1973 (Volume RG9.77, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Member List, 1974 (Volume RG9.78, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Member List, 1975 (Volume RG9.79, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Member List, 1976 (Volume RG9.80, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Member List, 1977 (Volume RG9.81, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Member List, 1978 (Volume RG9.82, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Series III. Dues Collection Records, 1838-1963; 3.21 Linear feet
  The Dues Collection Records series includes a variety of records related to the actual collection of dues and initiation fees from members. The bulk includes 24 volumes of receipt books from which were sent notices for payments. Aside from some unused blank receipts, these books only have the stubs remaining, some of which indicate the name of the person who was sent the associated receipt. There are three sets of these receipt books: regular annual dues (1838-circa 1855), life member dues (1847-1963), and new member initiation fees, which included dues for the first year (1849-1857, 1879-1939). There are also two books for Fellows and for Patrons; these have only a few entries in them from the early twentieth century. An annual dues receipt book for 1853 was discarded because it held mold spores; the content of the book can be gleaned from the other dues books of the early 1850s, which remain in the series.
  Many of the receipts sent from the annual dues books appear to have been returned to N-YHS without payment. This series includes those receipts, principally from the 1840s-1850s, many of which are annotated with the reason for non-payment.
  The series also includes a set of small booklets that were used to record monies collected, ranging from 1867-1921, with some earlier periods (1840s, 1857).
  The Dues Collection Records series is arranged by format, and chronologically within format. The series opens with the various certificate books from which were sent the forms notifying members of payments due, followed by booklets used to record collections, and closing with receipts and other documents concerning the payment or non-payment of dues. Although some receipts were found loose during processing, most were found in bound packets and these were kept together.
  - Annual Receipts, 1838-1843 [1844] (Volume RG9.83, Folder -)
  - Annual Receipts, 1844-1845 (Volume RG9.84, Folder -)
  - Annual Receipts, 1846-1847 (Volume RG9.85, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents from Receipts Book, 1846-1847 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Annual Receipts, [1848] (Volume RG9.86, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents from Receipts Book, [1848] (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Receipts for Dues, [1949?] (Volume RG9.87, Folder -)
  - Annual Dues, 1850 (Volume RG9.88, Folder -)
  - Dues, 1851 (Volume RG9.89, Folder -)
  - Dues, 1852 (Volume RG9.90, Folder -)
  - Dues, 1854 (Volume RG9.91, Folder -)
  - Dues, 1855 (Volume RG9.92, Folder -)
  - Initiation Fees, 1849-1852 April (Volume RG9.93, Folder -)
  - Initiation Fees, 1852 April-1857 (Volume RG9.94, Folder -)
  - Initiation Fees, 1879-1889 (Volume RG9.95, Folder -)
  - Initiation Fees, 1890-1895 (Volume RG9.96, Folder -)
  - Initiation Fees, 1895-1902 (Volume RG9.97, Folder -)
  - Initiation Fees, 1903-1909 May (Volume RG9.98, Folder -)
  - Initiation Fees, 1909 June-1924 (Volume RG9.99, Folder -)
  - Initiation Fees, 1925-1939 (Volume RG9.100, Folder -)
  - Life Certificates, 1847-1867 (Volume RG9.101, Folder -)
  - Life Membership Fees, 1868-1901 (Volume RG9.102, Folder -)
  - Life Membership Records, 1902-1948 January (Volume RG9.103, Folder -)
  - Life Membership Records, 1948-1963 (Volume RG9.104, Folder -)
  - Fellows, 1903-1909, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Patrons, 1904-1908, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - New York Historical Society Tax, 1840-1842 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Annual Receipts, 1840-1847 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Includes a booklet recording monies received for an unidentified year (likely 1846 or 1847) and various receipts for 1840-1847 found in the booklet.
  - Resident Members Proposed by W.K. Strong, 1857 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Though found with membership records, the amounts recorded in the booklet ($100 and $50) suggest that this might be related to a subscription drive for the N-YHS building or other matter.
  - Collector's Returns, 1867 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Collector's Book, 1868-1874 May (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Collector's Book, 1874 May-1883 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Collector's Book, 1884-1893 February (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Collector's Book, 1893 February-1907 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Collector's Book, 1908-1923 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Annual Dues Receipts (1 of 8), 1833-1842 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    This set of eight folders includes receipt certificates, most, and perhaps all, of which appear to have been returned to N-YHS without payment of the requested amount.
  - Annual Dues Receipts (2 of 8), 1841, 1844-1845 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Annual Dues Receipts (3 of 8), 1845-1848 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Annual Dues Receipts (4 of 8), 1844-1845, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Annual Dues Receipts (5 of 8), 1847-1849 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Annual Dues Receipts (6 of 8), 1848-1850 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Annual Dues Receipts (7 of 8), 1849-1851 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Annual Dues Receipts (8 of 8), 1852-1855 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Life Member Fee Receipts, 1850-1853 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Resignations & Life Members (Receipts), 1909-1921 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Membership Slips Returned by Members, 1943, 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Series IV. Miscellaneous Lists, 1804-1920; 1 Linear feet
  The Miscellaneous Lists series principally includes lists of members compiled at various times, mostly in the mid and late nineteenth century. Many of these lists include the address of the member and, in many instances, later annotations indicate the death of a member. Many of the lists are undated. The series includes two lists not related specifically to membership: a list of members paying to attend the 1904 N-YHS centennial dinner and a list of subscribers in 1849 to the N-YHS Proceedings.
  The lists are arranged in rough chronological order. Several of the lists are undated so their dates have been approximated. Several of the lists appear to have been added to and annotated over time and the date range shown does not necessarily reflect the range of those additions. Some of the lists are in chronological order by date of the members' election; the date range indicates the range of these election dates, not necessarily the date when the list or the individual entries were made. [Bracketed] titles were imposed by the archivist because an original title was not found on the list.
  - Catalogue of the Members, 1804-1841 (Volume RG9.105, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents from the Catalogue of Members, 1841, 1844 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes two lists: a list of members in chronological order of their election from 1804-1841 and a list of members who paid their dues for 1844.
  - Register of Annual Subscribers(?), 1804-1809, circa 1860s (Volume RG9.106, Folder -)
    Includes entries for a few members, those joining from 1804-1809. The few other notations in the volume are unrelated to memberships; these seem to date from the 1860s and refer to papers read and to items in the collection. The volume's cover is stamped "Stuyvesant Institute," which was N-YHS's home during the 1830s.
  - Manuscript Mailing Lists, 1845 (Volume RG9.107, Folder -)
  - [Member List], 1804-1846 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - [Member List], 1804-1848 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Subscribers to Proceedings, 1849 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - [Member List?], circa 1860? (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript Mailing List, circa 1860? (Volume RG9.108, Folder -)
  - Mailing Lists, Etc., 1862-circa 1890 (Volume RG9.109, Folder -)
    Includes pages from the printed 1862 N-YHS charter, by-laws and list of members, with annotations, member updates, addresses, dues payment status, death dates, and tipped-in lists dated to circa 1890.
  - [Member List], circa 1873 (Volume RG9.110, Folder -)
    The lists are recorded on the reverse of blank checks for the Mechanics' Bank.
  - Loose Document from the Member List, circa 1873 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Resident Members. Address Book, 1874 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Loose Documents from Resident Members Address Book, 1877 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Includes list "Loss of Resident Members."
  - [Member List (1 of 2). A-L], circa 1880s? (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - [Member List (2 of 2). M-Z], circa 1880s? (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Members, 1904 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Includes the printed list of members, with annotations.
  - [Centennial Dinner List?], 1904? (Volume RG9.111, Folder -)
    This volume appears to be a record of members who paid for themselves and a guest to attend N-YHS's centennial dinner.
  - Loose Document from the Centennial Dinner List, 1904? (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Member List (1 of 2). A-L, circa 1910s (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Member List (2 of 2). M-Z, circa 1910s (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - [Patron & Fellows Register], 1904-1915 (Volume RG9.113, Folder -)
  - [Membership Offers?], 1918-1920 (Volume RG9.112, Folder -)
    This volume appears to be a list of individuals offered membership in N-YHS in 1918-20, with notes on whether they accepted or declined.
- Series V. Certificates and Other Forms, circa 1843-1900s; 4.08 Linear feet
  The Certificates and Other Forms series includes blank print forms related to the membership process. Forms include those related to nominations, applications, and notices to new members of their election. These files are unlikely to be complete as to all the possible forms used over time in the membership process. The series also includes stocks of blank membership certificates; many of these are signed by an N-YHS president and other officers. Seven of the membership and twelve of the fellows certificates are made out to recipients.
  The series is arranged by format.
  - Blank Forms, circa 1860s-1890s; 0 Linear feet (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Blank Forms, circa 1900-1982 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Blank Membership Certificates, [1843-1844] (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Includes certificates signed by Foreign Corresponding Secretary Frederic DePeyster, Domestic Corresponding Secretary George Folsom, and First Vice President W.B. (William Beach) Lawrence.
  - Blank Membership Certificates, [1846-1847] (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Includes certificates signed by President Albert Gallatin, First Vice President Luther Bradish, 2nd Vice President Thomas DeWitt, Foreign Corresponding Secretary John Russell Bartlett, Domestic Corresponding Secretary John Jay, and Recording Secretary Andrew Warner. Three from 1846 are made out to Corresponding Members George Gibbs, Henry Hilliard, and H.W. Whiting and one from 1847 is made out to Honorary Member Ambrose Spencer.
  - Blank Membership Certificates, circa 1849-1863 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Includes certificates signed by President Luther Bradish, First Vice President Thomas DeWitt, and 2nd Vice President Frederic DePeyster. The certificates date from different periods and are signed by the secretaries from those periods: Foreign Corresponding Secretaries John Russell Bartlett, Edward Robinson, and George Bancroft; Domestic Corresponding Secretaries James William Beekman, and Samuel Osgood; and Recording Secretaries Andrew Warner and Maunsell B. Field. Two certificates, dated February 3, 1857, have seals and are made out to resident life members William L. Andrews and William J. Valentine.
  - Blank Membership Certificates, circa 1864-1899 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Includes certificates from the second half of the nineteenth century, signed by presidents Frederic DePeyster, Thomas DeWitt, Benjamin Hazard Field, and John Alsop King. Some are signed by secretaries, including Andrew Warner, George Bancroft, Samuel Osgood, John Romeyn Brodhead, Sydney H. Carney, Jr., and Frederic Wendell Jackson (pro tem). One certificate, dated April 4, 1899, has a seal and is made out to life member William S. Pelletreau.
  - Blank Membership Certificates, 1800s (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Blank Membership Certificates, 1800s (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Includes a shrink-wrapped set of blank certificates.
  - Blank Membership Certificates, 1800s (after 1843) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Blank Membership Certificates, 1901-1903, circa 1927 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Includes certificates signed by presidents Eugene A. Hoffman, Samuel Verplanck Hoffman, and John Abeel Weekes. Secretaries signing the certificates are Sydney H. Carney, Jr and Stuyvesant Fish.
  - Blank Honorary Membership Certificates, 1900s (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Completed Fellows Certificates, 1905 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Includes certificates signed by President Samuel Verplanck Hoffman and Recording Secretary Acosta Nichols, with seal, and made out to: Charles A. Hoyt, Collis P. Huntington, Adrian Iselin, Rachel L. Kennedy, Robert J. Livingston, Henry G. Marquand, Perry R. Pyne, Julia Rhinelander, William L. Skidmore, David Stewart, Charles L. Tiffany, and Robert Winthrop,
  - Blank Fellows Membership Certificates, 1900s (Box 8, Folder 1)